<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a person in the countrey to his friend in the city: giving his judgement upon a book entituled A healing question.</title>
            <author>Person in the countrey.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87933</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1420</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E885_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202810</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862981</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862981</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168399</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87933)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168399)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E885[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a person in the countrey to his friend in the city: giving his judgement upon a book entituled A healing question.</title>
                  <author>Person in the countrey.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Vane, Sir Henry.  A healing question propounded and resolved upon occasion of the late publique and seasonable call to humiliation.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: June 14. 1656.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August 16 1656".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Vane, Henry, --  Sir, 1612?-1662. --  Healing question propounded and resolved upon occasion of the late publique and seasonable call to humiliation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168399:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Letter from a Perſon in the Countrey to his friend in the City: giving his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon a Book entituled <hi>A healing Queſtion.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have received your Letter, with the printed Paper in it entituled <hi>A Healing Queſtion propounded &amp; Reſolved, &amp;c.</hi> &amp; your commands with it to give you my poor ſenſe upon it: In obſervance of which I preſent you this, which if it much exceede the limits of a Letter, I have only this to ſay, that 'tis in obedience to your orders; and that the guilt thereof is contracted alone againſt him who is the occaſion of it; for I write not for any mans ſight but yours.</p>
            <p>I have indeed peruſed it, and I may ſay not without ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſity and by as to the Authours deſign, becauſe of its carrying with it, as I heard, the approbation and conſent of ſome honeſt men. I think truly there is as much ſaid in it as the Argument can well bear, yet not ſo much but may be well anſwered, and if not by me, yet by ſome other who may have better time and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities for ſuch a work: But if in telling you my thoughts upon the whole, I leap from one page over the Heads of many others, it is not done by deſigne, but by neceſſity, the matter being ſo diſpoſed of by our Author that I could not avoid it. In his third Page he mentions two Generals from which all his other particulars are derived; and thoſe are, to uſe his own words, <hi>The Honeſt Peoples juſt natural Right in Civil things, and true Freedome in matters of Conſcience.</hi> I ſhall beg your and our Authors pardon if I tranſpoſe his Order, and give things of the firſt concernment the firſt place, by which I am tyed to proceed to anſwer that Head under this Title, <hi>of true Freedome in matters of conſcience:</hi> which he hath defined, and given Reaſons for, from the latter end
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168399:2"/>of his 5. page, to near the middle of the 8. But therein I doubt twil be found, that he to be ſure to binde up the Magiſtrate, hath ſet at liberty all others.</p>
            <p>I ſhall willingly agree with him, That in things of the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and Higheſt concernment, all poſſible tenderneſſe ought to be exerciſed by the Magiſtrate. But I muſt beg this excuſe if I cannot think that in things of that nature he is wholly exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. He may ſin in two extreames; In not doing, and in over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing; And me thinks, even what our Authour himſelf ſayes, <hi>That the Nations of the world have Right and Title by the Purchaſe of Chriſts blood to Freedom in Spirituals;</hi> doth at leaſt evince, That none have right thereunto, which do not own him, by whom only they can have that right, &amp; therefore were all others exempted from that power; ſuch are not. Who ſhall puniſh blaſphemers or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers of him that bought them? (A herefie branded by the Spirit it ſelfe by the name of damnable.) Churches, as ſuch, cannot do it adequately to the Crime, ſince the higheſt of their actings is to ſeparation or excommunication; and what puniſhment is it for him that believes there is no God or Chriſt, to be excluded from his publique Worſhip, and ordinances? hath God taken care that his Glorious Name ſhould not be blaſphemed, from the beginning till Chriſts time, and afterwards doth not regard it to the end of the world? nor is it competent to ſay that in the new Teſtament we read of no ſuch power exerciſed by any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians as Magiſtrates: ſince it is evident that after ſome yeares that the Lord Chriſt was come in the fleſh, there were no Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates which were Chriſtians; but ſince any have been, it hath been both the duty and care of the good from time to time, by puniſhing, to beare their teſtimonies againſt ſuch evills, yea even when wickedneſſes have aſſumed the names of religion; for Satan can transform himſelfe into an Angel of light, a truth too evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and ſad in our dayes to be denied by any.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ingenuouſly confeſſe to you (Sir) I begin to ſuſpect thoſe moſt which in ſoul concernments do cry for liberty moſt; the Biſhops, how bitterly did they inveigh againſt the inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors? and how ſoone, and exactly, when they got the power, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came they ſuch? the Presbyterians whom the Lord made the rod to whip thoſe, you ſee how our Authour whips them with the names of perſecutors, towards the cloſe of his 7 page, and from them flies to the next ſort of Clergie (I wiſh his quarrell be not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168399:2"/>to thoſe of that calling) for he ends there, when, alas, too many others are even perſecuting thoſe Clergie as far as they can, that is, with their tongues, and if not puniſhed and deterred by the Magiſtrate, would queſtionleſſe do it with their Hands alſo; for 'tis, as to the puniſhing of others, a ſhort and eaſie ſtep from declaring the guilt to acting of its penalty. I have truly my ſelfe heard ſome averr, that they eſteemed it a religious duty to call ſuch as we owne to be Miniſters of the Goſpel, hirelings, dumbe dogs, <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts, and ſellers of the gifts of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; where note by the way, theſe franticks confeſſe theſe ſaid Miniſters they ſo miſcall, have the gifts of the holy Spirit; elſe they could not make merchandize of them; for they cannot ſell what they have not; nay they are either ſo ignorant or malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as to allow them the beſt gift, to accuſe them for imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it the wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> way, but if they have it, He enſure their accuſers they cannot ſo diſpoſe of it; now I would gladly know where but from the Magiſtrate ſhall ſuch oppreſſed be relieved? ſince from ſuch people themſelves, we cannot hope they will puniſh any of their owne number, had they any diſcipline amongſt them; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that which is their fault, is a part of their religion: but it may be ſaid that this is a cleare acted evill, and therefore cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcible by the Magiſtrate. I ſay ſo too; but thoſe which are guilty of it will deny it, and alleadge ſome internall dictate or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe carried them to do it, and therefore 'tis a part of their worſhip, to act what the Magiſtrate and others think a part of their duty to puniſh. If it be ſaid they are miſtaken; I deſire to know who are competent judges therein; and they will anſwer in our Authors owne words, <hi>p.</hi> 6. about the midſt of it; <hi>Why ſhouldeſt thou ſet at nought thy brother in matters of his faith, and conſcience, and therin intrude into the proper office of Chriſt ſince we are all to ſtand before his Judgment ſeat, whether Governours, or governed, and by his diciſion only are capable of being declared with certainty to be in the right or in the wrong,</hi> ſo that if you puniſh or reſtrain ſuch people, you deny, according to what our Authour ſayes, that right which the Nations of the world are intitled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by the Purchaſe of Chriſts blood; and if you do not, you tye up the ſheep of the flock, whilſt you let looſe the Wolves, &amp; while you cry up liberty, you allow &amp; authorize perſecution; I ſay perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, though it be only of the tongue; and how ſore a one that is, the Spirit doth in divers places, witneſſe, <hi>Job</hi> 5, 2. it is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168399:3"/>called the ſcourge of the tongue. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.4. The tongue is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a ſharp ſword. And to paſs by a cloud of other witneſſes in this behalf, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.18. it is ſaid by the ungodly there, which conſpired againſt the Prophet, <hi>Let us ſmite him with the tongue;</hi> which evinces this ſort of perſecution is not only known to be one by the bad, but felt as ſuch by the good; nay, <hi>Michael</hi> the Arch-Angel, <hi>Jude.</hi> 9 verſe, though contending with the Divell, durſt not bring againſt him any rayling accuſation; and totally to ſtop the mouths of ſuch perſecutors, and to manifeſt whilſt they raile they cannot pretend religion for it, ſee what <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.26. <hi>verſe If any man ſeem to be religious amongſt you, and bridle not his tongue, that mans religion is vain.</hi> A cleare and Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Scripture, &amp; ſuch as we have as much cauſe to credit is Chriſts ſentence in that caſe, as if we had heard him pronounce it; ſo that we need not doubt herein, or leave that to his finall Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in Heaven, which he by his Spirit hath given us ſo expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citely on earth: we may as well if any Blaſpheme God, or deny the moſt Eſſentiall Fundamentals in Religion, leave that alſo till the laſt Judgement to determine with certainty whether ſuch a man be therein in the right or in the wrong, as leave ſuch men only to ſuch deciſion; wee have nothing more for this than we have for that; therefore I fear the Latitude our Authour propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes will be ſo far from weaning the people from that Biting, devouring, wrathfull ſpirit he mentions, that it will but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke and allow it. It is eaſier for authority to bridle Men than for men to bridle themſelves; elſe why are there lawes eſtabliſhed in civil, or diſcipline in ſpirituall things? ſuch avowed Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, as genuinely, and naturally tend to the deſtruction of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety and government are not to be tolerated in any, though aſſumed under the ſpecious and high pretence of Religion, which is ſo far from being deſtructive to either that it is the beſt and ſtrongeſt foundation and Cement of both. Who ſhould have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt thoſe franticks of Munſter but the Magiſtrate? ſhould their p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea of conſcience have tied up his hands? and would any (but of their number) have had him let them murther as many as they would or could, and have ſtayed till the Laſt day to have had it judged with certainty whether their murdrings by their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded religion had been right or wrong? Or ſhould any in theſe dayes aſſume their principles could any think the Magiſtrate
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168399:3"/>without Breach of Truſt and duty could waite patiently till they were acted? I am certain if it would be too ſoone for him to do any thing before, then it might be too late for him to do it afterwards; how if a growing ſociety of men ſhould own as a Scripture truth that none have title to be governours, but the ſaints (though truth it ſelfe hath told us, that the Kingdome of the King of the Saints is not of this world, &amp; that having food and raiment only, wee ſhould therewithall be content) and that none are ſaints but themſelves; every Magiſtrate therefore that is not of that feather, muſt be either excluded, or be judge over his brothers conſcience; who hath ſo complexed, and inter-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven things of government, and things of conſcience, that none can ſeparate the one from the other, nor be a judge in one, but in both.</p>
            <p>I ſhall, Sir, willingly and clearely agree, that in opinions of religion, though their profeſſors differ from the truth in the judgement of the Magiſtrate, yet if they are ſo innocent as to be prejudiciall in their act or in their direct conſequence unto none but thoſe which imbrace them, all poſſible gentleneſſe, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance ought to be exerciſed towards ſuch; and it is a Duty to endeavour their reſtoring in the ſpirit of meekneſſe, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring leſt we alſo be tempted; but I beſeech you (Sir) obſerve how our Authour deſignes that the liberty he mentions, ſhould not be infringed, viz. <hi>Even by laying a reſtraint therein upon the ſupreame Power before it be erected, and this as a fundamentall conſtitution amongſt others, upon which the free conſent of the people is given to have their Perſons brought into the exerciſe of the ſupream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over them, and on their behalf, as it is expreſſed, towards the middle of the</hi> 7th. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g.</hi> By which, methinks, it is evident that our Authour would have no ſupreame Authority ſet up till they are tyed to that which would make them merit to be pulled down; &amp; I muſt plainly confeſſe, I know not who thoſe can be (according to his grounds) which can lay a reſtraint upon the ſupreame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, either before or after its erection; For it muſt be either by a part of the good people, or by all; it cannot be by all; for the reſtraint muſt be laid before all be met in a capacity to act, and it is an act to lay a Reſtraint; and if by a part, by what right can they lay reſtraints upon the whole? that were to doe what the Authour moſt complaines of; how ever I will make uſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168399:4"/>of this paſſage in this ſeventh page, to reply to a part of his thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen page, wherein he laments, and earneſtly asks, <hi>why ſo refined a party of men are not inſtructed with their right?</hi> which queſtion I will anſwer with another, if they are not capable and fit to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with their rights, why doth he complain that they are not? and if they are, why would he denie them, and fetter them in the things of the nobleſt concerment, or doubt their honeſty, if this particular be not their right, that they would declare ſo much, ſince it is in a matter ſo evident and cleare as he alleadges this is.</p>
            <p>But that you may ſee whether this refined party did fight for that Liberty he mentions, obſerve I beſeech you what they did either in their defuſive capacity, or as repreſented in or by their Parliament, in which moſt properly they ſpeak and act.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, you ſhal have our Authors own words &amp; obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to cleare it, which alſo he accompanies with this expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>that it is a thing will not ſuddenly be out of memory, viz. when the laſt King made war againſt the Scots, he was deſerted by all the good people of England; whereby it is evident, thoſe which he calls perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Presbyters,</hi> were owned as good men by the good people; and whether thoſe do allow of his freedome is as cleare by the title he gives them of perſecutors. As to the ſecond, I appeale to his owne conſcience, whether he doth not know, and believe that the people repreſented in the long Parliament, (and I think he will owne none other ſince which have acted, to be a true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative) had not begun to eſtabliſh, and would not have continued that diſcipline in Church affaires which he cals Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting: ſo that as yet whatever hath been declared by the people diffuſively or collectedly, hath been contradictory to our Authours liberty. And poſſibly this may be the cauſe why, though he cries them up for ſo refined a party and fit to be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, yet that in this particular he would binde up their hands abſolutely &amp; not truſt them at all, I wil hope our Authour is not popiſhly inclined, becauſe of his expreſſions in the latter end of his ſeventh Page <hi>(viz) That by what be propoſed a great part of the outward exerciſe of antichriſtian Tyranny and Bondage would be pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked up by the roots.</hi> Yet permit me to ſay, if his notion be practiſed, he hath left as free a latitude for the exerciſe of the profeſſion of the Papiſts, as for the profeſſion of the Truth, and this I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168399:4"/>the Honeſt party of this Nation never did deſign; and if our Author does, he had need truly to ſhackle and manacle their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative before they fit, ſince they will never doe that to themſelves after they ſit. But that you may ſee how little cauſe our Author hath to be offended in this particular, read but the 36, 37, and 38. Articles of the Government, wherein ſo large a latitude is allowed in matters of conſcience, that I think no man hath reaſon to repine that he hath not enough. I wiſh ſome good men do not think, if any cauſe of complaint be, it be not on the other hand. But if our Author will not credit the Government, I deſire but that he will credit himſelf, to evince the truth of what I aſſert; For in the upper part of his eight Page he makes uſe of theſe very words, <hi>That therein</hi> (viz. <hi>true Freedome in matters of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience) the preſent Governours have been willing very eminently to give their teſtimony in their publique Declarations; ſo that what grievance is found amongſt us therein, is in probability more from the officiouſneſs of ſubordinate Miniſters than otherwiſe.</hi> Our Author not condiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending to ſet down either wherein ſuch ſubordinate Miniſters have been too officious, or the perſons who have been ſo, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks evidences that any cauſe of grievance therein is rather pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended than acted; For if any ſuch really and actually had been, tis not likely they had remain'd uncomplained of, ſince thereby one of theſe two Ends had been attained, a <hi>Redreſſe</hi> of the ill, <hi>or,</hi> failing thereof, a clear Diſcovery that ſuch Declarations and Laws were only intended to delude and not protect ſuch tender conſciences; either of which carry in them too much cauſe of ſatisfaction or complaint to have been uneſſayed, had there been grounds for it: And tis very improbable that our Governours ſhould make Lawes not to obſerve them, whereby they muſt not only have been found guilty of Hypocrifie, but alſo by ſleighting their own Rules in ſome caſes have invited the people to have done the like in many, if not in all others.</p>
            <p>Having thus <hi>(Sir)</hi> expreſſed unto you my poor apprehenſions concerning this one General relating to <hi>true Freedome in matters of conſcience;</hi> I ſhall proceed to the other, which is, <hi>the Peoples juſt Right in civil things,</hi> which our Author makes chiefly, if not only, to conſiſt in enjoying the Freedome to ſet up meet perſons in the place of ſupreme judicature and authority amongſt them; In which I believe, things being throughly examined, there will
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168399:5"/>remain as little cauſe of complaint as in the former; For in that particular the government hath been ſignally and juſtly careful to provide, as may appeare from the ſixth to the twenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fifth Article of it, by which we are more ſafe therein than ever we yet were, and poſſibly as ſafe as the nature and quality of ſuch a thing can well admit: But perhaps our Author is not ſatisfied that any which have been againſt us, ſhould be reſtored, after three Triennial Parliaments, to a capacity of being elected, or of becomming electors of Members in ſucceeding Repreſentatives: If that be the quarrel (as ſome of his expreſſions ſeem to inferr) I ſhall deſire him to read but his own words about the midſt of his ſeventeenth Page, wherein he ſaies; <hi>If as the Foundation of all, the Soveraignty be acknowledged to reſide originally in the whole Body of adherents to this cauſe, whoſe natural and inherent Right thereunto is of a far antienter date than what is obtained by ſucceſs of their Armes, and ſo cannot be abrogated even by conqueſt it ſelf, if that were the caſe, &amp;c.</hi> Which words if true, methinks clearly prove, that our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors have done thoſe people whom we through the providence of God have conquered, more wrong in debarring them ſo long, then the Good people in debarring them no longer; For if it be ſuch a natural and inherent Right that even conqueſt it ſelfe cannot abrogate it, how come they to loſe it? And if it be ſaid that none have a Right thereunto but by adhering to the Good cauſe, then our Author contradicts himſelfe, ſince he ſaies this Right is of a far antienter date than what is obtained by ſucceſſe and armes. But in my opinion the Wiſdome and Care of thoſe which compiled the Government, is ſignally evident in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; for ſo long our enemies are excluded as a competent time to wear out that heat and animoſity which they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted againſt their conquerours; As alſo to let them relliſh and throughly know the ſweet and benefit of this Government above that which they contended for; And poſſibly too, as a time for triall of their good behaviour, which tis likely they cannot coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit ſo many years: And they are excluded no longer, nor for ever, leſt it ſhould perpetually entaile thoſe Diviſions which in wiſdome and charity we ſhould endeavour to Heale and Cement. Beſides, our Author neere the latter end of his twentieth Page mentions, as a neceſſary thing, that when the ſupreme authority ſhould be convened, according to his device, one of their firſt Acts
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168399:5"/>ſhould be to paſs an Act of Oblivion, which doubtleſs is not that our enemies ſhould forget they ever had a Right and Title to elect or be elected; Or if this be meant, I think all things elſe will appear rather a Name than a Thing.</p>
            <p>But ſince that contraries being oppoſed, doe the better illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and ſet forth each other, let us take a proſpect of what ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> condition was before the war, and our now government, and what 'tis by it. The King was never bound to call a Parliament, at leaſt never did but when he could hardly avoid it: the Protector i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tied to call a Parliament every third yeere, ſometimes oftner. The King when a Parliament was call'd, could or did at his pleaſure diſſolve it: the Protector when a Parliament is called, cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve or prorogue it without its own conſent till five moneths b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> effluxt, a time competent to make or repeal Laws, and call t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> account and puniſh the great offenders, the true and proper end of Parliament. The King had or aſſumed a Negative Voice to al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bills preſented to him by the Parliament; Or at leaſt denye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them with a French complement, <hi>Le Roy S'aviſera:</hi> The Protector hath but twenty dayes Deliberation, and then if not by common conſent altered, they paſs without him. The King in the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals of Parliament was not yoaked with any council which had a Negative upon him: The Protector is. The King choſe all his Council: The Protector, excepting the now Council which could not be a avoided, in effect chooſes no more; but the people doe it in their Repreſentatives; for they nominate All that are to be choſen, though the Protector out of ſuch ſo nominated does at laſt chooſe; And for the Council that now are, what can Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments deſire more than if they Govern well to have the people enjoy the Benefit? If ill, themſelves to avoid the Blame, to act the redreſſe, and to impoſe the Puniſhment? Had a Parliament no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated the Council, they could have had but the ſatisfaction of their own opinions that the Council would have acted as they ought; and the opinion of an Aſſembly never made a man other than he is; But the Punitive power being ever in their Hands, they are as ſafe as a thing of that nature can admit; No authority can prevent a mans being evil, it can but puniſh him for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> having been ſo. The King made all his great Officers in the three Nations without the Knowledge or Conſent of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: The Protector can make none without both. The King
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168399:6"/>commanded the <hi>Militia,</hi> abſolutely; and by our deſiring it from him, even when our Priſoner, we implicitely owned that right was in him; the Protector can doe nothing with the Militia, a Parliament ſetting without their conſent; and in their intervals without the councill, who are a kind of repreſentative of the people. The King not only as ſuch, but by vertue of the Laws had thereby ſo enſnared the conſciences of good men, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being Rebels they could not ſhun being Martyrs if they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in this Commonwealth: the Protector by the government hath taken off thoſe <hi>Inquiſition-like</hi> and ſevere Lawes, and not only doth admit but protects all ſuch as profeſſe faith, in God by Jeſus Chriſt, though differing in judgement from the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, worſhip and diſcipline publiquely held forth, ſo that they abuſe not this liberty to the civill injury of others, nor to the actuall diſturbance of the publique peace, and do not under this profeſſion hold forth and practice licenciouſneſſe: provided that liberty extend not to Popery. A whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome proviſion which our Authors liberty hath quite left out or forgot.</p>
            <p>Theſe, beſides many others, are the rich and high fruits of thoſe victories which the Lord in Mercy hath given his people, which are ſuch, that if any things are capable to compenſate the expence of ſo much time, treaſure, and precious blood, theſe are; and indeed wee ſeem hardly to want any thing but grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full quiet ſpirits, under what we poſſeſſe. By all which it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that the peoples juſt rights in civil things (which our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor makes chiefely, if not only to conſiſt in free national aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies) are not only comprehended in the government, but ſo explicitely ſet down that he which runs may read, which makes mee hardly abſtaine from repining at any man that ſhall endeavour to looſe this knot, and caſt away our preſent certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, only to try new experiments and concluſions; but poſſibly our Author wil not be ſatisfied, unleſſe things of a civil nature be left at as much uncertainty as thoſe of a ſpiritual; for towards the latter end of his 20 page, he hath <hi>theſe expreſſions (viz) the people repreſented in their higheſt ſtate of Soveraignty, as they have the Sword in their hands unſubjected unto the rules of civill govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but what themſelves aſſembled to that purpoſe do think fit to make.</hi> By which he ſeems to inferre, that by our ſucceſſe we have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168399:6"/>fought our ſelves into nothing but what hereafter ſhall be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed. I thinke very few men when the war began, did engage in it upon that account, and for that end; for my part I did not, though in prayers, in counſel, in perſon, and in Purſe, I have been of it from the firſt day till this houre; the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by their declaration ſtating the grounds of their taking up Armes, which invited all the good people thereunto, mentioned no ſuch thing; but on the contrary enumerated thoſe rights which were denied to them, and thoſe wrongs which had been obtruded on them; the firſt of which they ſought to obtaine, and the laſt to repaire and vindicate; and indeed to my poor capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city it would ſeem a kinde of enchantment, thatthings proſecuted ſhould be real &amp; certaine when they were fought for, and ſhould turne into ſhadowes &amp; notions when acquired by the defeat of him who denied them. It would doubeleſſe extenuate the crime of the common enemy in doing what they did, had they known we deſigned what our Author doth; no doubtleſſe, we had a known right to fight for before Armes were taken up, which by victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly defending, and regaining we have not loſt; but perhaps ſome may ſay, our Author aſcribes this boundleſs power to what the people duely aſſembled in their Repreſentatives may act; but I finde what he ſpeakes is not of what they may doe, as an effect of their Authority, but what is done as an effect of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</p>
            <p>Our Author proſecutes his treatiſe in telling us firſt the qualifications of the perſons which have adhered to this cauſe; ſecondly, the capacity wherein they have been found from time to time carrying it on. As to the firſt, he ſayes, <hi>they have conſtantly ſhewed their forwardneſſe in it, in Purſe, Perſon, or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell as the cauſe is truly ſtated in the two branches thereof, already ſpoken unto,</hi> as it is more largely expreſſed from the midſt of his 8 page, to the midſt of his 9 page; only I am to obſerve that one marke of their qualifications, hath been that in order to thoſe ends, they have ſtood by the Army in defence and ſupport thereof, againſt all oppoſition whatever; that is, not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the common enemy, but againſt the Parliament it ſelfe; firſt, when one of its two eſtates did not their duty, and alſo when the other ſailed in theirs. And the Author doth give you an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent reaſon for their having ſo done, (viz) <hi>As thoſe that by the grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing light of theſe times have been taught &amp; led forth in their experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168399:7"/>to look above and beyond the Letter, Form and outward Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Government, into the outward Reaſon and Spirit thereof, therein only to fix and terminate, to the leaving behind all empty ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes that would obtrude themſelves into the place of true Freedome.</hi> Which words are expreſſed about the midſt of his ninth page; And I believe are ſet down by him, not only to juſtifie what is paſt, but to authorize what may be acted in the future; for if it be allowable in preceding times, it may in parallel or reſembling caſes be allowed in times to come; And what a gap or rather breach this would open for all confuſions and diſorders, is ſo cleare, that to ſpend any time in illuſtrating of it were to make it ſeem leſs evident than it is. Doubtleſs (Sir) we of the Army had a better Warrant for what we did than this aſſertion of His; And if breach of poſitive engagements on the one ſide, and of an invincible neceſſity on the other, could or did ever authorize ſuch procedure as ours, we ſhall have no more cauſe to bluſh in owning it than I hope we ſhall ever have again to repeat it. But I ſhall not inſiſt upon this point, becauſe I write only for, and to a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that I know hath no doubts in it.</p>
            <p>I will now return to obſerve what conſiſtency there is between my Authors expreſſions in his foregoing words of the ninth Page, and his ſubſequent ones in the tenth; In which, having erected his ſupreme judicature, he tels us; <hi>unto the wiſdome of their Laws and Orders the ſword is to become moſt entirely ſubject and ſubſervient, and this without the leaſt cauſe of jealouſie or unſafety to the ſtanding Army, or the Good People adhering to this Cauſe.</hi> But ſuppoſe that the Army or a part of the Good people ſhould diſlike the actings of their ſupreme judicature, (as what hath once been, may rationally be thought may be again) and this upon the account (as they may alledge) of the growing Light of theſe times; And how far it may grow before it ceaſeth God only knowes, ſince even in a few years time it hath been Bright enough to ſhew <hi>Some</hi> (as our Author would have it) how to look above the letter, forme, and outward circumſtances of Government into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Reaſon and Spirit thereof, and to make ſome individuals better and more competent Judges of all theſe, than thoſe which even thoſe ſelf ſame individuals had impowered to judge and act for them; Nay, than ſuch as all the whole Nation had Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed for the like ends; Our Author in ſuch a Caſe either muſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168399:7"/>not allow this Latitude to ſome particulars above the whole, and thereby exclude them from the benefit of this extraordinary growing Light, which once was wiſely and happily made uſe of; and therefore may the better be truſted unto to Act againe by; Or muſt allow it them; and then that ſubjection and ſubſerviency mentioned by him, vaniſhes by his own confeſſion into Aire, and with it not only the form but eſſence of all Government. He muſt I doubt extinguiſh this new growing Light ere he calls his ſuprem judicature; or elſe it will grow neer to extinguiſh them.</p>
            <p>But indeed our Author in the ſame ninth Page when he comes to acquaint us with the capacity wherein theſe perſons qualified as aforeſaid have acted, He tels us very ingenuouſly; <hi>[That it hath been very ſeldome if ever at all ſo exactly and in all points conſonant to the Rules of former Laws and conſtitutions of Government as to be clearly and fully juſtified by them any longer than the Law of ſucceſſe and Conqueſt did uphold them who had the inward warrant of juſtice and righteouſneſſe to encourage them in ſuch their actings.]</hi> What this inward warrant is cannot with more difficulty be made out than if allowed at all, eaſily pleaded and aſſumed by any as well as the Good people: But ſince ſuch inviſible warrants may be indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently pretended by Both, 'twil be wiſedome to leave no Riſe for their being pretended unto by either; which, God be praiſed, our now Government hath done.</p>
            <p>In our Authors 16, and 17th pages He does much complaine that any Party ſhould ingroſs and aſſume to themſelves the office of Soveraign Rule and Power, and impoſe themſelves as the competent judges of the ſafety and good of the whole, without their free and due Conſent, Adding; <hi>That this is that Anarchy which is the firſt ſtep and riſe to Tyranny, and layes the Grounds of manifeſt confuſion and diſorder, expoſing the Ruling Power to the next hand that on the next opportunity can lay hold on the ſword. &amp;c.</hi> But he will doe well to Remember that he hath not only already allowed this, but commended it; And how if hereafter a part of the whole again ſhould have an inward warrant to pretend the like, will not he permit ſuch to try by the Law of ſucceſs and Conqueſt to uphold that inward warrant of juſtice and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs which encourages them in ſuch their actings? twil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hard to commend this in ſome, and condemn it in others; Nay twill ſeem unjuſt not to permit thoſe which have the principle it
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168399:8"/>ſelfe, to try to act that, which only can, and, which if it ſucced ſufficiently will (as our Author ſayes) juſtifie it.</p>
            <p>But indeed it is harder for us of the Army to have our Caſe thus egregiouſly miſtated, though we muſt confeſs we are very much obliged to our Author, who having ſo wrongly ſet it down, does yet excuſe us in it, nay does extoll that in us, which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſayes will be the way to Anarchy, confuſion and Tyranny in all others.</p>
            <p>If our Author be not a Souldier, ſure he hath a mind to be one; for he tels us in the midſt of his tenth page, <hi>That the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary intereſt and capacity is the intereſt &amp; capacity of the whole Body of the good people, &amp; that in that poſture they are moſt properly ſoveraign, and poſſeſs their Right of Natural ſoveraignty.</hi> For my part, I ſhall clearly confeſs I do not underſtand that there is, or ever was ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally a natural ſoveraignty in any Society; For no Society is by nature, but by pact or agreement; and till ſuch pact or agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, every individual was naturally in a ſtate of War, like <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael</hi> whoſe hand was againſt every one, and every ones hand againſt him, which wild and unſafe ſoveraignty all men being ſenſible of, laid it down upon agreed on conditions, by which all were obliged to help each other in the defence of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Bargain; So that no Body of People have ſoveraignty by nature but by pact; And we have doubtleſſe a better and more firme Right than this natural one which our Author mentions; I mean a Legal Right, to which all have ſubjected themſelves explicitely, and by which no evaſions are left for Diſobedience, at leaſt fewer than in that natural Right our Author mentions, which poſſibly never was, nor ever will be defined in all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars and branches of it. But if our Author be not already a Souldier, I think it will be beſt to keep him from being one. For he that talks of the Army's Continuing as long as the good People, which he clearly does in the latter end of his tenth page, wherein he mentions <hi>Their continuing every one with their Army,</hi> is not fit to be of it; for I verily believe there are few, if any, amongſt us (at leaſt known or avowed) but are more troubled there is cauſe to keepe up the Army, than they would be that there were none, and they forthwith disbanded. But before I proceed farther, permit me I beſeech you to obſerve one expreſſion more in the ſame page, (viz) <hi>The good peoples Army raiſed by them,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:168399:8"/>wherein he doth ſure allude to what ſhould be if his Utopla tooke place; &amp; conſequently that a new Army ſhould be raiſed; or elſe why is it ſaid raiſed by them? Continued by them, had been more ſignificant &amp; clear, if his ſenſe had not been ſuch as I underſtand it to be; and indeed all his expreſſions are ſo full of ſtrength and light in what he doth ſet down, that this expreſſion makes me the more confident I have hit upon his intentions in thoſe his words, which if I have, many genuine Inferences may be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by collected, which may well manifeſt the deſigne our Author drives at, but indeed are too voluminous for a Letter.</p>
            <p>But I cannot omit one paſſage of his in his 11. page towards the midſt of it, (viz) <hi>The Army putting themſelves with their fellow Adherents to the cauſe under the Rule and Authority of their own ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Judicature, they loſe not their Power or ſoveraignty; but by becomming one civil or Politique incorporation with the whole party of honeſt men they doe keep the ſoveraignty, as originally ſeated in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and part with it only but as by deputation, and repreſentation of themſelves when it is brought into an orderly way of exerciſe, by being put into the hands of Perſons choſen and intruſted by themſelves to that purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which words he would infuſe into the people, that the Army believe they have acquired the ſoveraignty over all; which, if true, might juſtly render us worthy of the hatred even of our friends and brethren; nay by his words he not only makes us enſlavers of the people in this age, but may poſſibly make us the like in ages to come; for if the original right is in us as the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and we part with it but by deputation, we may as well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call our right from thoſe to whom we ſhall depute it. Whereby the Army ſhall become indeed the ſupreame Authority, and as our Author hath deſigned it, the Army ſhall alwaies be.</p>
            <p>We are, the Lord knows, but too ill of our ſelves, and need no ſuch Painters, who through deſigne, or ignorance, draw us worſe than through mercy we are, or I truſt ever ſhall be; he ſayes, we are lovely in thoſe clothes he hath Clad us with, but makes all others to be monſters which ſhall weare the like. Having now I hope evinced unto you, that by the government we are now through providence under, the people enjoy true free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in matters of conſcience &amp; their juſt right in civil things, &amp; thoſe to be conveyed to them by their Repreſentatives duely cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168399:9"/>and not fettered or manacled, as our Author would have them, I ſhall now proceed to what remaines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He tells us in his firſt and</hi> 2 <hi>pages, That this cauſe hath ſtill the ſame goodneſſe in it as ever, and is as much as ever in the Hearts of the good people who have adhered unto it; that it is not leſſe to be valued now, than when neither blood, nor treaſure were thought too dear to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it on; that the perſons engaged in it, are ſtil the ſame as before, with the advantage of being more tryed, more inured to danger &amp; hardſhip, &amp;c.</hi> All which being granted, methinks, doth clearely infer that the good people, by their continuing quiet, do evidently confeſſe they have got what they chiefly contended for; or that what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines unacquired, is not worthy to be ſolicited by engaging in new warres, or hazarding what through mercy they now poſſeſs; poſſibly we have not all we aimed at, and poſſibly it is well for us as well as others that we have not. There are many things men would endeavour to obtain, when a war is made, which they wil not make a war to obtain; beſides it is likely we are but too po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive in not acquieſcing in any thing ſhort of all we drove at, which may have juſtly provoked the Lord to have denied us our hearts wiſh, that we might have more of dependency upon his good wil, &amp; leſs of eſtimation for our own deſigns &amp; reſolutions.</p>
            <p>Our Authour tels us that <hi>if a ſupreame repreſentative, were conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted as aforeſaid, hardly afterwards any new thing would ſtick, as to the forme of adminiſtration, and deſcends to a ſtanding councill of ſtate ſettled for life, whoſe orders ſhould bebinding in the intervalls of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional aſſemblies as far as they were conſonant to the ſettled Lawes; the vacancy or death of any of which to be ſupplied by the vote of the Major partof themſelves</hi> (but herein the people are more behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the government, than to our Authour; for by it, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their Repreſentatives, chooſe ſuch counſellors, and do not permit them to chooſe themſelves, which if allowed, might entaile both them &amp; Faction, upon the people) Nay he continues) <hi>would there beany juſt exception to be taken, if it ſhould be agreed as another part of the fundamentall conſtitution of the government, to place the branch of ſoveraignty, which chiefly reſpects the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lawes, in the hands of one ſingle Perſon, and for the greater ſtrength and honour unto this office, that the execution of all Lawes and orders, that are binding, may goe forth in his name, and all diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience thereunto, and contempt thereof, be taken as done to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168399:9"/>ſoveraignty; whereof he bears the Image or repreſentation &amp;c.</hi> And then again in the ſame 18 page. <hi>Would ſuch an office as this, thus ſtated, carry in it any inconſiſtency, with a free ſtate? Nay, if it be well conſidered, would it not be found of excellent uſe, to the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being of Magiſtracy, founded upon this righteous bottome, that ſuch a Lieuetenancy of the peoples ſoveraignty, in theſe three Nations, may alwaies reſide, in ſome one, or ſome more perſons, in whoſe adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that which is reward and puniſhment, may ſhine forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By all which, Sir, you may evidently perceive he is ſo far from being againſt thoſe main hinges and Pillars upon which our Government moves, and by which it is ſupported, that he gives pregnant and ſtrong arguments for them; only he would have the people doe it, and I ſay they have done it already, even in the choice of their laſt Parliament, and in the Parliament it ſelfe; nay, I dare averre that never any Government in the three Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, was more fully and explicitely owned by the people, than this now in exerciſe hath been; neither ever yet was any forme of Government more clearly expoſed to the peoples judgements, nor received by them than this hath been. I am certain that Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth was not, which we ſo lately have extricated our ſelves out of, and which poſſibly our Author may not be undeſirous to have us revert unto; for that mutation was made only by the remnant of a Repreſentative, in which too many of the people had none to ſpeake or act for them: But this forme of Government we now are under <hi>(viz.)</hi> by a ſingle perſon and a Parliament, was ſent down into every Shire and County of the Nations, that none (except enemies and people not worth 200. <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr>) might pretend ignorance, or be denied his opinion and vote; and upon ſuch proofe and tryal, the people not only embraced it, but even tied every individual of their Repreſentative not to alter it. But our Author may ſay, that indenture by which they did ſo, was ſent down to them to ſign; and I ſay, but it was ſigned by them; the Government did but offer the condition, but 'twas the people did accept it; Our Author may farther ſay, 'twas a few of the people did ſo; to which I anſwer, that either thoſe which did it were the greater or the leſſer number of the people; If the leſſer, how comes it about the greater did not oppoſe it? if the greater, the objection ceaſes. If all are ſummon'd, and all doe not appear, thoſe which do are to be reputed as all; elſe no election could be made or eſteemed valid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Author ſpeaks of a general Council or Convention to be called
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168399:10"/>by the preſent power, but conſidered as general,</hi> which Convention, though choſen by the Body of all the Adherents <hi>to this Cauſe, are not yet to exerciſe their Legiſlative power, but only to debate freely and agree upon the particulars that by way of fundamental conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall be laid and inviolaby obſerved as the condition upon which the Body ſo repreſented doth caſt it ſelf into a Civil and Politique In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporation, &amp;c.</hi> as is more at large ſet down in his 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>page.</hi> I beſeech you Sir take notice of theſe words [<hi>the Body of all the Adherents to this Cauſe</hi>] without taking care (as anciently) that none but freeholders ſhould chooſe or be choſen in Shires; or as our Government hath now well provided, that none ſhall chooſe or be choſen, but perſons worth 200 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> that is, men who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably by their ſubſtance have not only ſome competent degree of underſtanding who to chooſe, but alſo ſome intereſt and cauſe to chooſe well, as having purſes which are likely and capable to feel it, if they do otherwiſe: By which wild Latitude (if allowed) we might come to have as odde work in things of a civil concernment, as our propoſed liberty in ſpirituals is like to leave us in, in ſoul concernments. Indeed a civil Authority ſo choſen is likelier to introduce ſuch dangerous liberties, than a Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative choſen either by the old or the new rules.</p>
            <p>But though I muſt commend our Author, who having propoſed the end, ſets up the readieſt way to attain it; yet I more commend our Government which hath ſo well provided againſt our great Repreſentative's being in a capacity to be choſen by the Refuſe of the people, or to be compoſed of them.</p>
            <p>Having made this (I think) needful digreſſion, I ſhall now beg your leave (Sir) to ſpeak a few words both to <hi>the thing propounded, and to the manner of acting it: To the thing,</hi> It is to be an aſſembly to agree upon fundamentals of Government; which were in effect to do leſs well for the people then the Government hath already done; for there is no queſtion if 'twere practicable for all the people of the three Nations to tranſact their own buſineſs by themſelves without Repreſentatives, it would be more clear and ſatisfactory for them to do it in that way than in the other; And though the people do chooſe thoſe people for their Repreſentatives which they moſt truſt in, yet they truſt more in themſelves than in ſuch ſo choſen: Beſides, it often ſo falls out, that many of the people are unavoidably Repreſented by perſons whom they have not choſen; nay, againſt whoſe choiſe they have actually declared, as is evident in the voices for Knights and Burgeſſes, where the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168399:10"/>majority of votes (though but in one) excludes all others that are voted for: Theſe being irrefutable truths, I cannot but commend the wiſedom and ingenuity of the Government, and the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the people, that an affair of this nature ſhould be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered ſo advantagiouſly, that in the main form of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>(viz.)</hi> whither it ſhould be by a ſingle perſon and a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they have not been left implicitely as our Author propoſes, to the ſenſe of their Repreſentatives, but have been made the clear and proper Judges thereof themſelves; by which it would be hard to tell, whither the people are more actually obliged in what the Government hath done; or intentionally diſobliged in what the Author propoſes. Let this model propoſed be but well conſidered, and let every reaſonable man be judge; our Author would have an aſſembly choſen by all the Honeſt Party, which ſhould agree upon fundamental conſtitutions of Government; which for ever after, the ſupream Legiſlative power ſhould be obliged unto, and ſhould not have power to alter. Doe but ſee in this what a weak thing all our Authors diſcourſe turns upon; Theſe fundamentals are to be agreed upon by the peoples Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives, and to oblige the ſupream Legiſlative power (which is to be the peoples Repreſentatives alſo) ſo, that the peoples Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives once met, are to oblige their Repreſentatives for ever after: which is a thing not only abſurd in it ſelf in the nature of it, but of the higheſt improbability in the practice of it; for who can dream that Repreſentatives of the people, when choſen and met, will ever hold themſelves obliged by any conſtitutions of former Repreſentations, farther then they ſhall according to time and circumſtance agree with their liking? ſince they all ſtand upon one foot of power, as entruſted by the people; and the latter may as well, and by as good right alter conſtitutions and laws agreed by the former, as the former could make ſuch: ſo that if our Author will truſt the peoples Repreſentatives at firſt to make fundamentals, by as good reaſon he may truſt them ever without any at all, ſince that the power and choice of obſerving or not obſerving thoſe fundamentals will alwayes reſt in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and this unavoidably ſo: Doubtleſs the beſt way to convince our Author, were, a liberty given him to put in practice his own new-framed Government; for then he would not fail to find and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment that unreaſonableneſs and impracticability in it, which he doth not now ſee: Let but all matters of Government be left as <hi>raſa tal ula,</hi> to all the Honeſt Party who have adhered to this good
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168399:11"/>Cauſe, and I believe, whither you reſpect them by themſelves or in their Repreſentatives, they will ſo little agree with any of our Authors principles, from the beginning to the end of his Booke, that I doubt he would <hi>recurre</hi> again to that growing light he ſpeakes of, to make but letter and forme of ſuch <hi>conventions,</hi> (as he ſeems formerly to have done) and find out ſome other way to juſtifie and bring about thoſe things he aimes at: Certainly our Author may deſign the overthrow of the preſent Government, by defacing and blemiſhing of it, but cannot intend the ſetting up of his own; he muſt needs know the force of his principles laid down (if they have any) is more offenſive to the preſent power, then any way defenſive to themſelves. I have read moſt Hiſtories, and do not remember that ever the like to this hath been practiſed; either thoſe in power in erecting of Governments wanted the ability to find out ſo happy an expedient, or the honeſty, if 'twas found out, to afford it to the people. Our paſt Kings indeed had a faint ſhew of ſomething like this; for at their Coronation, ſome few that aſſiſted at it, were demanded whither they would have the perſon to be Crowned to be their King: But the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt this and that is vaſtly great; for firſt, This was not to the forme of Government, but to the perſon which was to governe. Secondly, This was not to the people of the Nations, but to ſome deſignedly or accidentally there. Thirdly, (to omit many other differences) As they were not ſolemnly convened from all the Shires of the Nations, (neither indeed could be, or their mindes generally known but by that way the now Government hath pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed) ſo neither was there any thing of their aſſents given either formally or legally. The contrary of all which is evidently to be found in the now forme of Government, which at once doth manifeſt the unwillingneſs of thoſe in power to ſet up any model of Government that the people in their largeſt capacity did not like, as alſo that the people did fully like this; both which are ſo fignal and rare, that I beg your excuſe, if that beliefe hath made me dwell too long upon this particular.</p>
            <p>The next thing is, as to the <hi>Manner</hi> of calling ſuch Conventions, It muſt be by the preſent power conſidered as a General; and then our Author ſayes, <hi>What is done by it, is not in Danger ever to be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, being made by the People in their Higheſt State of Soveraignty as they have the Sword in their hands, &amp;c.</hi> This, Sir, I fear will be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to many inconveniences; ſome I ſhall inſtance beſides thoſe I have ſet down already.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:168399:11"/>
            <p>Firſt, it Authorizes a General, as a General, to Call a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and if once the Protector, as a General, does doe that, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after Generals ſucceſſively may pretend to the like priviledge, and ſo our Government become purely Military; To invite us to which, Our Author calls that, <hi>The Peoples higheſt State of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, in which they have their Swords in their Hands.</hi> But poſſibly He may ſay, the now Protector as General did once already call a Parliament; to which I anſwer, He indeed Call'd an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, but 'twas that Aſſembly Call'd themſelves a Parliament; Beſides, that was by his Call, not the peoples Election. Secondly, If ſuch a Convention were met, they might perhaps agree to have a Supreme Magiſtrate (which too our Author doubts not of) who by his Office ſhould call Parliaments, and the General (if ever the Generals and chiefe Magiſtrates Offices ſhould be diſtinct) by that precedent, might pretend to the like, by which we might have at once two Parliaments by two Authorities, both having ſpecious pretences for both, which might prove too fruitfull a ſeed for putting the people too often into their Higheſt State of Soveraignty.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Though the Protector could aſſume the Chiefe Magiſtracy of this Nation, yet he cannot Righteouſly relinquiſh it or the Government, if (to uſe our Authors own words in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Caſe) Declarations to men and Appeals and Vows to God fignifie any thing.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It will be madneſſe in the Protector to annihilate that Government of himſelfe, which the People both by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Repreſentative have ſo far approved, only to call a Convention to try if they can light upon a Government which the people may approve, which were no other in effect than to take the Authors Opinion in the behalf of the people rather than their own in their own Behalfe, and that too doubly Declared. Would not ſuch a proceeding make us Ridiculous both to our ſelves and the world, to be ſo often changing Foundations, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in this Caſe wherein ſo little of Advantage can either be enjoyed, or ſo much as hoped for? I cannot truly believe that our Author can rationally expect that thoſe in preſent Authority ſhould relinquiſh a Government which many Thouſands have explicitely owned and embraced, only to accept of a Propoſal which he alone does offer; If he will be but patient till he can bring as many clear proofes that his Notion is approved of by the People, As the Government can that it is ſo, it will be then
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168399:12"/>a fitter time to Liſſen to him than Now; And till then it will be but juſt, that the ſenſe of the Major part of the good people con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude His or the Minors, And herein I hope the government doe obſerve the Royal Law.</p>
            <p>I omit, Sir, Many other things, becauſe I cannot ſo much wrong my argument in doing ſo, as I might your patience in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing otherwiſe; but as our Authour hath had his conjecture, that nothing, as to a ſingle perſon, would ſtick in his propoſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention; ſo give me leave to have my doubt, that, that it ſelfe would there ſtick, and if it ſhould, who then could put a period to a Repreſentative, if it endeavoured to perpetuate it ſelf as ſome ſuch thing I have heard, was in deſigne? And if the Protector had not plaid the Protector, before he was ſuch, it might have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo been turn'd into act. <hi>The people would then have had a good time to have complained to their Repreſentative againſt their Repreſentative;</hi> and a worſe, if they had endeavoured to have righted themſelves by war, which yet would have been the only remedy. This thing alone doth, if nothing elſe did, ſufficiently evince the good and neceſſity of a ſingle perſon impowered, as the Protector is, by the government.</p>
            <p>I ſhall agree with our Authour, that there is a high and viſible neceſſity for all the people that have hitherto embraced our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon cauſe, to unite themſelves, were it only in point of ſecurity againſt a common enemy, who is not out of work though at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent out of ſight (but I fear out of the Authors obſervation, by his propoſal) I would gladly deſire that the inclinations and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſity thereunto were as ſtronge as the cauſes and incentives are; it were happy if all good men, eſpecially thoſe of ſuch ſignall and eminent parts, as he by his treatiſe ſeems to be M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſter of, would employ them to make the beſt of what is, rather than to perplex &amp; blemiſh it, &amp; thereby give opportunity to that common enemy, he may ſo juſtly apprehend, to think our diſſatisfactions many and great, &amp; improve his own intereſt by ſuch knowledge.</p>
            <p>I muſt crave his pardon if I cannot agree with him in what he mentions in his 22. Page, (viz.) <hi>That for theſe three yeares laſt paſt, there hath been a great ſilence in Heaven, as if God were pleaſed to ſtand ſtill and be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Looker on.</hi> I wiſh that what is his ſaying of Heaven, had been his own practice upon Earth; Many of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies then had been ignorant of that he accuſes the Government of, and I freed from the trouble of anſwering ſuch his Accuſation: I muſt clearly confeſs what he ſayes in that particular is ſo far
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168399:12"/>from being, in my Apprehenſion, a truth, that it is a high mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake. And poſſibly I might not erre in ſaying, that the providence of the Lord hath hardly been more active for good in ſome ages paſt, than in but a part of that time, in which he ſayes the Lord hath ſtood ſtill, and been but a looker on; to evince which, conſider <hi>I</hi> beſeech you, ere this government began, how unſettled &amp; perplexed was our own nation? Scotland &amp; Ireland, large parts of this Common-wealth, all in a flame; we engaged in a bloody war by ſea with the Datch; the French, the Spaniards, the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal, the Swede, and the Dane at beſt no friend, if not actual ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. But as ſoone as it was eſtabliſhed (wherein, they ſaw wee were come to a hopefull conſiſtency) as the firſt effects and fruits of it, part of them paid for their peace, and all the reſt implored it; Our Internall warres forthwith were quenched; ſo that in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, when our enemies ſaw us become wiſe, they became ſo to; And the Terror of the Lord was upon all thoſe who before had ſought our Ruine, which might be an effect of his gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, When a Mans wayes pleaſe the Lord he maketh even his Enemies to be at peace with him: If a Sparrow falls not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Providence, doubtleſſe ſuch conſiderable Changes and Events are not ſignes that God hath ſtood ſtill and been a Looker on; but rather that they are the products of his care and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards his people, who may provoke his higheſt Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by their ſo meanly eſteeming of his higheſt Mercies. 'Tis true indeed we are now engaged in the War with <hi>Spain;</hi> but it is as true that the Provocations and Cauſes of it were too Great any longer to protract it, which is ſo clearly ſet down in the printed ſtate of that War, as to receive ſatisfaction therein, one need but to Read that: tis confeſt that hitherto this War hath not proved ſo promiſing and ſucceſsful as many were confident it would, which I feare may have in part occaſioned it: But who ever obſerves the uſual Method of Gods Diſpenſations towards us, he will find even this it ſelfe is proportionate to moſt others: Our Loſſes in the beginning being but to try our Faith; And as this hath been parallel to many others in the firſt part of it, ſo I truſt it will be the like in its Concluſion and Event.</p>
            <p>I am certaine it is not ſo conſiderable as only upon its own account to give the Author a R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe to believe that God hath been pleaſed for three years laſt paſt to ſtand ſtill and be a Looker on; To which there is but one thing elſe that I can call to mind as a pretence to authorize this his Belief, and that is, the Protectors
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168399:13"/>and the laſt Parliaments not Cloſing, which truly was a cauſe of ſadneſs to all Honeſt Hearts; but tis hoped that the unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof will be by experience ſo ſet home upon all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, that it will the more ſtrongly incline affections to an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the next which is called, and therby though it did not prove our Bleſſing then, yet it may prove the cauſe of it in the future.</p>
            <p>Our Author ſayes in his ninth Page, <hi>One Mark or Qualification of the Good People was their ſtanding by the Army in maintaining of their Cauſe.</hi> I wiſh that Mark and Qualification may yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinne, and as the Armies of the three Nations have by expreſſe Addreſſes fortified the hands of the Government by their owning and Declaring for it, ſo that our Author and All the other Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt People would fortifie their Hands alſo in doing the like, that as Union hath hither to been the evincement of our good affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo now that it might be of our wiſdome. Let our Author allow towards the ſettlement of this Government but ſome of that growing Light he commended in pulling down the former, and all may do well. Actions unconſonant to Laws and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of Government, are much more tolerable for building up peace than for Diſſolving it. Methinks it may ſerve to quiet the Mind of the Author and Others to Conſider that what we have is much more than we deſerve; and that by repining at having no more, we may provoke the Eyes of Gods Glory, and invite him to make us feel we have too much. Let us mend our inward Condition, and then our outward one will follow. <hi>Let us ſeeke firſt the kingdome of God and his Righteouſneſs, and all ſuch things ſhall be added unto us.</hi> If this Government be not of God, let man endeavour what he will to ſupport it, it will fall: And if it be of God, let man endeavour what he will to ſuppreſs it, and it will ſtand. Let us therefore with patience expect what Iſſue he will be pleaſed to give it; For God is the Judge, who in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as well as perſons, putteth down one and ſetteth up ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. That good Advice, <hi>Meddle not with thoſe which are given to Change,</hi> is as pertinent for our Times as poſſibly for Any ſince 'twas firſt ſpoken. There is a Scripture much upon my Heart (and with that I ſhall Conclude) which containes, what every one is to doe; then what All are to expect, and what to avoid. <hi>I will hear what God the Lord will ſpeake, he will ſpeake Peace unto his People and to his Saints; but let them not turn again to Folly;</hi> which that They may not, is the earneſt and Hearty prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>June</hi> 14. 1656.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours in the Beſt and ſureſt Bond.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
